Sampson County CR.087
State Archives of North Carolina
- Court Records, 1784-1968; CR.087.3; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  - Minute Dockets, Other Courts, 1881-1968; CR.087.331; 287.34; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    - Criminal Minutes [Docket], County Court, 1957-1968; CR.087.331; 2004.9.59; 287.34.3; CR.087.331.4 - CR.087.331.8; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Criminal Minutes [Docket], County Court)
  - Inebriates, Lunacy, and Judicial Hospitalizations Records, 1900-1968; CR.087.919; 287.94; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Access Restrictions
    These records are restricted by NCGS 122C-207. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
    Records include documentation of hearings for commitment of insane persons and inebriates, listing the name of the alleged lunatic, oaths of parties testifying to his/her lunacy, and copies of the clerk's order of commitment and the superintendent of the state hospital's order of release. Papers may include appointment of guardians to oversee the property of the unfit. After 1899, the clerk was required to keep lunacy matters in a distinct volume, entitled Record of Inquisition of Lunacy or simply Lunacy Docket. From 1868 to 1899, lunacy proceedings were recorded in the Orders and Decrees (922).
    See also Court Records subseries 922, Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings.
    - Record of Lunacy, 1900-1968; CR.087.919; 287.94.1; CR.087.919.1 - CR.087.919.5; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Lunacy)
      Access Restriction
      Court records pertaining to judicial hospitalizations are closed per NCGS 122C-207. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
    - Inquisition of Inebriates, 1940-1963; CR.087.919; 2003.4.26; 287.94.2; CR.087.919.6 - CR.087.919.7; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Inquisition of Inebriates)
  - Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings, 1867-1941; CR.087.922; 287.106; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Includes records created in hearings before the clerk. These have sometimes been distributed among other series of records based on subject: see also Court Records subseries 919, Inebriates, Lunacy, and Judicial Hospitalizations Records; series 4, Land and Property Records; series 5, Estates Records; and series 6, Marriage, Divorce, and Vital Statistics, subseries 604, Divorce Records, and subseries 901, Adoption Records, if available.
    - Miscellaneous Orders and Decrees, Index, Notary Public and Railroad Police, 1913-1941; CR.087.922; 2016.11.39; 287.106.1; CR.087.922.24; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Miscellaneous Orders and Decrees, Index, Notary Public and Railroad Police)
      Also contains petitions and appointment of guardians.
    - Special Proceedings Papers, 1867 - 1906, undated; CR.087.922; 2017.6.102; 287.106.2; CR.087.922.1 - CR.087.922.23; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Special Proceedings Papers, Box Unprocessed Special Proceedings #288-4741)
      Processed, chronological. Unprocessed, file number order
      Special proceeding records from 1867-1906 are processed chronoligcally. Unprocessed special proceedings papers #288-4741 are in roughly file number order and housed in 25 letter boxes.
  - Minutes, Court of Pleas & Quarter Sessions [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 167; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Court of Pleas & Quarter Sessions)
  - Equity Minute Docket [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 144; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Equity Minute Docket)
  - Minutes, Superior Court [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 10; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Superior Court)
  - Judgment Docket, S. C. [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 11; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Judgment Docket, S. C.)
  - Judgment Docket, Land Sales [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 355; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Judgment Docket, Land Sales)
  - Index to Judgments - Land Tax [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 334; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Judgments - Land Tax)
  - Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens - Plaintiffs [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 137; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens - Plaintiffs)
  - Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens - Defendants [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 136; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens - Defendants)
  - Minutes, Inferior Court [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 49; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Inferior Court)
  - Minutes, County Court [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 15; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, County Court)
  - Minutes, Recorder's Court [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 169; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Recorder's Court)
  - Index to Civil Actions [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 17; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Civil Actions)
  - Index to Criminal Actions [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 18; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Criminal Actions)
  - Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 19; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Judgments, Liens & Lis Pendens)
  - Lunacy, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 108; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Lunacy, Record of)
  - Inebriety, Inquisition of [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 110; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Inebriety, Inquisition of)
  - Orders and Decrees [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 140; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Orders and Decrees)
  - Special Proceedings [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 6; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Special Proceedings)
  - Index to Special Proceedings - Plaintiffs [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 142; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Special Proceedings - Plaintiffs)
  - Index to Special Proceedings - Defendants [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 141; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Special Proceedings - Defendants)
  - Index to Special Proceedings [Microfilm], C.087.30000; 116; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Special Proceedings)
- Land and Property Records, 1810-1956; CR.087.4; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  This series contains records related to ownership, transfer, and taxing of land and property.
  - Deeds, 1926-1956; CR.087.401; 2018.8.270; 287.108; 287.108.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Register of Deeds. (Box Unprocessed Deeds)
    Records stored in the State Records Center require additional time to pull. Access to these records on Saturdays requires prior arrangements. Please consult the reference staff for more information.
    Records are unprocessed. Records include original deeds left in the courthouse after being deposited with the clerk for probate and recording. These loose deeds can include various types such as deeds of sale, deeds of trust, mortgage deeds, and quitclaim (or release) deeds. Within these records, the seller is commonly referred to as the grantor, the buyer as grantee.
  - Land Divisions, Partitions and Surveys, 1811-1927; CR.087.406; 287.41; Petitions; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    May contain volumes and/or papers concerning divisions of land between tenants in common and the processioning of boundary lines between contentious neighbors. These records may include volumes of land division, Record of Surveys, and Record of Processions, as well as loose papers of petition for partition or sale of land (taken from actions at equity and, after 1868, Special Proceedings) and processioners' records.
    See also series 3, Court Records, subseries 325, Civil Action Papers, and subseries 922, Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings.
    - Record of Surveys, 1895-1911; CR.087.406; 287.41.1; CR.087.406.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Surveys)
    - Land Divisions, 1811-1927; CR.087.406; 287.41.2; CR.087.406.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Land Divisions)
  - Land Sale for Taxes, 1930; CR.087.407; 2016.11.38; 287.107; 287.107.1; CR.087.407.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Land Sold for Taxes)
    Records may include volumes and/or papers pertaining to the sale of land for nonpayment of taxes.
  - Miscellaneous Land Records, 1810-1928; CR.087.408; 287.43; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    May contain two types of miscellaneous records: (1) papers from the other land records series that were of insufficient quantity to make up their own box and were thus comingled in the same box, and (2) true miscellaneous papers and volumes concerning land which do not fall into any of the enumerated land records series. These true miscellaneous records include condemnation proceedings; foreclosures; attachments, executions, liens, and levies on land; and volumes relating to the probate of deeds.
    - Attachments, Executions, Liens, and Levies on Land, 1825-1920; CR.087.408; 287.43.1; CR.087.408.1- CR.087.408.3; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Attachments, Executions, Liens, and Levies on Land)
    - Miscellaneous Land Records, 1810-1928, no date; CR.087.408; 287.43.2; CR.087.408.4; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Miscellaneous Land Records)
      Alphabetical
      Contains commissions to take private examinations of various parties concerning conveyances, 1870; deeds, 1810, 1864, 1883, 1890, 1892, 1896, 1901; description of the land of Abram Hobbs, no date; ejectments, 1836- 1869 (broken series); ejectments (summary proceedings), 1870-1918 (broken series); ex parte proceedings concerning land, no date, 1860-1926 (broken series); in re: sale of the lands of Edd D. Kornegay and wife under mortgage sale, 1928; land entries, 1906-1909; land processions, 1874, 1876, 1878-1880, 1883; mortgage deeds, 1877, 1884, 1891, 1898, 1907; note for land, T.N. Culbreth and W.R. Culbreth to William McKenzie, 1859; plats, no date, 1888, 1889; receipts for land, 1867, 1870, 1895, 1908, 1909; reports of land sales, no date, 1846, 1867, 1868, 1896; surveyor's report of the county line between Sampson and New Hanover Counties, 1846-1847; transfer of bid for land, 1869.
  - Homestead and Personal Property Exemptions, 1869-1923; CR.087.914; 287.89; 287.89.1; CR.087.914.1- CR.087.914.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Homestead and Personal Property Exemptions)
    May contain records pertaining to insolvent debtors (1773-1868) and/or homestead and personal property exemptions (1868-). Records include applications of debtors, oaths, notices to creditors, property schedules of insolvents, and reports of committees to lay off homesteads exempted from forced sales. May also include homestead returns.
  - Record of Deed [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 1; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Record of Deed)
  - Real Estate Conveyances [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 3; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Real Estate Conveyances)
  - Deeds of Trust [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 2; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Deeds of Trust)
  - Land Grants [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 60; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Land Grants)
  - Surveyor's Records [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 245; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Surveyor's Records)
  - Index to Federal Tax Liens [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 53; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Federal Tax Liens)
  - Land Division Records [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 50; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Land Division Records)
  - Satisfactions (Cancellations) [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 61; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Satisfactions (Cancellations))
  - Maps/Plats [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 33; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Maps/Plats)
  - Index to Plats (Maps) [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 56; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Plats (Maps))
  - Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantors & Grantees [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 57; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantors & Grantees)
  - Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantors [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 4; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantors)
  - Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantees [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 5; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Grantees)
  - Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Trustee [Microfilm], C.087.40000; 318; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Real Estate Conveyances - Trustee)
- Estates Records, 1784-1969; CR.087.5; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  This series contains records related to the administration of deceased persons' property.
  See also series 3, Court Records, subseries 922, Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings, and series 4, Land and Property Records, for other records related to estates.
  - Estates/Accounts, Dockets, 1830-1969; CR.087.EA; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains bound volumes of account, inventory, and/or settlement records related to the administration and settling of deceased persons' property. These include Record of Estates (pre-1868), Record of Accounts (post-1868), Accounts of Sales and Resales of Estates, Record of Inheritance Tax, Inventories of Estates, Amounts Paid Indigent Children, and Record of Settlements. Prior to 1868, volumes entitled record of estates may include inventories, accounts and final settlements of estates, and guardians' accounts. After 1868, these volumes in most counties contain only inventories, accounts of sales and annual accounts of administrators and executors.
    - Record of Estates/Accounts, 1830-1968; CR.087.501; 287.45; Accounts; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
      Prior to 1868, volumes entitled record of estates may include inventories, accounts and final settlements of estates, and guardians' accounts. After 1868, the series in most counties contains only inventories, accounts of sales and annual accounts of administrators and executors.
      - Record of Estates, 1830-1868; CR.087.501; 287.45.1; CR.087.501.1- CR.087.501.8; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Record of Estates)
      - Record of Accounts, 1868-1968; CR.087.501; 2003.4.26; 287.45.2; CR.087.501.9 - CR.087.501.32; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Accounts)
    - Inheritance Tax Records, 1924-1969; CR.087.513; 287.57; 287.57.1; CR.087.513.1 - CR.087.513.5; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Inheritance Tax Records)
      Twentieth-century record of settlement of tax assessed on estates worth more than $2000 provided to the clerk of superior court by the State Commissioner of Revenue. Statements include names of deceased and administrator or executor, approximate valuation of estate, and heirs or devisees. Loose papers concerning inheritance tax are filed in the series of estates records.
    - Amounts Paid Indigent Children, 1930-1937; CR.087.515; 2004.9.59; 287.59; 287.59.1; CR.087.515.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Amounts Paid Indigent Children)
      Volume 1. Twentieth-century record of Clerk of Superior Court in his administration of estates of less than $300 (later $500) which accrue to orphans without guardians. Also includes accounts of clerk in his capacity as receiver of estates of orphans without guardians.
    - Record of Settlements, 1869-1946; CR.087.518; 2003.4.26; 287.61; 287.61.1; CR.087.518.1 - CR.087.518.7; Accounts; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Settlements)
      There are no records for 1935-1939. Volumes of settlements or final accounts submitted by administrators and executors after the complete distribution of the assets of an estate.
  - Estates/Accounts, Papers, 1784-1968; CR.087.508; 2009.12.77; 287.52; 287.52.1; CR.087.508.1 - CR.087.508.115; CR.087.508.116 - CR.087.508.16; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Estates Records)
    Alderman-Zachary. (Box CR.087.508.162 contains miscellaneous estates records, various dates).
    Contains loose estate papers, which may include appointments and renunciations of executors and administrators; administrators' and guardians' bonds; inventories; accounts of sale; annual accounts; final settlements; civil actions and executions involving administrators, executors, and guardians; and actions in equity or special proceedings involving property of an estate. If the father of wards can be determined from guardians' papers, they are filed with the estate of the deceased rather than with the guardians' records.
  - Administrators, Executors, and Guardians Records, 1803-1968; CR.087.AG; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains bound volumes and/or loose papers of bonds, appointments, and accounts of administrators, executors, and guardians. The loose papers consist primarily of guardians' records; loose administrators' bonds are generally filed in subseries 508, Estate/Accounts, Paper.
    - Administrators' Bonds, 1854-1908; CR.087.503; 287.47; 287.47.1; CR.087.503.1- CR.087.503.4; Bonds (legal records); Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Administrators' Bonds)
      Volumes arranged chronologically. Loose bonds are filed in the series of Estates Records (508). After 1919, see Appointment and Record of Administrators (504).
    - Record of Guardians, 1914-1968; CR.087.506; 287.50; 287.50.1; CR.087.506.1 - CR.087.506.5; Appointments; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Guardians)
      Post-1868 record of appointment and qualification of guardians. After 1919, includes oath and bond of guardians. Prior to ca. 1915, guardians were included in an omnibus volume entitled Appointment of Administrators, Executors, Guardians and Masters; in some counties, these are entitled Record of Probate (Estates) or Minutes, Probate Court (both in 519). May also include an index to guardians and wards.
    - Guardians' Records, 1803-1968; CR.087.510; 2009.12.78; 287.54; 287.54.1; CR.087.510.1- CR.087.510.32; Sampson County (N.C.). Register of Deeds. (Box Guardians' Records)
      Arranged alphabetically, Adams-Wynne (Box CR.087.510.32 contains miscellaneous guardians' records, various dates).
      Loose guardians' papers arranged alphabetically by surname of wards, and volumes of guardians' accounts (but see 509). Papers may include appointments, oaths and bonds of guardians; annual accounts; final settlements; civil actions and executions involving guardians; and actions in equity or special proceedings involving the property of a ward's estate. These records also include indigent wards for whom the clerk of superior court served as receiver. If the father of the wards can be determined from the papers, they are filed with the estate of the deceased rather than with the guardians' records.
    - Guardians' Bonds, 1854-1914; CR.087.511; 287.55; 287.55.1; CR.087.511.1 - CR.087.511.3; Bonds (legal records); Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Guardians' Bonds)
      Volumes arranged chronologically. Loose bonds are filed in either the estates records (by decedent) or the guardians' records (by ward). After 1919, see Appointment and Record of Guardians (506).
  - Accounts & Sales of Estates [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 86; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Accounts & Sales of Estates)
  - Index to Division of Land [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 385; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Division of Land)
  - Estates, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 20; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Estates, Record of, Reeldtl Estates, Record of)
  - Accounts, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 21; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Accounts, Record of)
  - Index to Annual Accounts [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 364; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Annual Accounts)
  - Bonds, Administrators [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 22; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Bonds, Administrators)
  - Administrators, Records of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 23; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Administrators, Records of)
  - Bonds, Guardians [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 68; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Bonds, Guardians)
  - Guardians, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 85; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Guardians, Record of, Reeldtl Guardians, Record of)
  - Index to Guardians [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 75; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Guardians)
  - Index to Estates [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 72; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Estates)
  - Index to Estates - Administrators, Executors & Guard [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 73; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Estates - Administrators, Executors & Guard)
  - Index to Estates & Wards [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 187; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Estates & Wards)
  - Inheritance Tax Records [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 77; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Inheritance Tax Records)
  - Indigent Children, Accounts of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 337; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Indigent Children, Accounts of)
  - Settlements, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.50000; 34; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Settlements, Record of)
- Marriage, Divorce, and Vital Statistics, 1869-2009; CR.087.6; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  This series contains vital records pertaining to major life events such as marriage, divorce, adoption (restricted by statute), immigration and naturalization, death, and disinterment/reinterment.
  - Divorce Records, 1869-1971; CR.087.604; 287.67; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains divorce actions pulled from Civil (and sometimes Criminal) Actions and/or record books of divorced women, which notes maiden name of divorcee and the date of notice of intention to resume maiden name. See also series 3, Court Records, for divorce case files, if available.
    - Divorce Records, 1869-1921; CR.087.604; 287.67.1; CR.087.604.1- CR.087.604.4; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Divorce Records)
    - Record of Maiden Name of Divorced Women, 1939-1971; CR.087.604; 2004.9.59; 287.67.2; CR.087.604.5; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Record of Maiden Name of Divorced Women)
      Volume 1
  - Disinterment/Reinterment Permits, 1968-2009; CR.087.607; 2016.8.70; 2017.1.84; 287.105; 287.105.1; CR.087.607.1; Sampson County (N.C.). County/District Health Departments. (Box Disinterment/Reinterment Permits)
    Alphabetical by surname of deceased or cemetery.
    Contains county copies of permits to disinter bodies and rebury them.
  - Alien, Naturalization and Citizenship Records, 1911-1940; CR.087.902; 287.77; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains records pertaining to the naturalization of foreign-born citizens, in which the clerk of Superior Court acted as federal agent. May include Declaration of Intent to Become a Citizen, Petitions for Naturalization, and/or Alien Registration, which notes name, age, nationality, address, previous address, and the names and addresses of five persons who knew each foreign-born citizen registering.
    - Petitions for Naturalization, 1911-1914; CR.087.902; 287.77.1; CR.087.902.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Petitions for Naturalization)
    - Alien Registration Record, 1927, 1940; CR.087.902; 287.77.2; CR.087.902.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Alien Registration Record)
  - Marriage Register [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 97; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Marriage Register)
  - Index to Marriages [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 151; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Marriages)
  - Maiden Names of Divorced Women [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 94; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Maiden Names of Divorced Women)
  - Index to Vital Statistics - Births [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 91; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Vital Statistics - Births)
  - Index to Vital Statistics - Deaths [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 92; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Vital Statistics - Deaths)
  - Index to Vital Statistics - Delayed Births [Microfilm], C.087.60000; 93; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Vital Statistics - Delayed Births)